hi welcome back to nigarina um
i made a mistake at the end of the last
class i said oh we're finished with the
chapter
but we're not uh we're still in the same
chapter i think it's chapter 16 which is
about
talking about
being chained to satsara
and then getting nirvana which is
releasing the chains and getting away
from satsang
and this second half of this chapter
doesn't take very long to teach so i
thought you guys might like to see
something so you could appreciate
uh you know
the work of trying to translate these
texts trying to find these texts
you know so
you're kind of at the end of the
of the food chain you know you are
speaking of chains
you are
getting you know all this information
all these teachings
because of other people
who work so hard to
find the books
catalogue the books
uh scan the books
input the books save the books and i'm
talking about you know a-l-l
and all of the hard work they do so you
know i kind of
i'm my part is the easy part i just
explained something
uh
that i ha i get the book because other
people have worked so hard for
over 30 years
uh to find these books and and to bring
me books you know they're like these
guys that go out in the world and find
the books and they bring them back home
and i get to sit and read them
and share them with you so i i kind of
wanted to recognize that
huge effort of john brady
and his whole team
of all and also all the gold clubs and
the club dioros and around the world and
all of you guys are working so hard
uh to raise money and i think sometimes
if i'm you
i would think well what do they do with
the money where's the money going you
know and i thought you would appreciate
uh seeing
how your donation became this class
okay so
first of all uh
the donations made
22 years ago
all right they went into we were trying
to find
chonin llamas books
and uh they were you know
it's in those days
it was very hard to get a copy of any of
tony llama's books
and my my teacher showed me one book
of chonilla and i was like wow
and i studied he has 250 books like this
come on rinpoche give him to me he's
like no you can't get him
and i was like what do you mean we can't
get him he says
we made a mistake and i'm like who's we
he says my monastery is there i mean we
made a mistake i'm like well what's the
mistake he says we didn't want other
monasteries to get charlie llama's books
because then we could win all the
debates
with the other monasteries so we kept
all of chili llama's books very
carefully i'm like what happened he said
well we kept them in the library
and i'm like what happened to the
library says well during the cultural
revolution the library was bombed
and it all burned up every copy burned
up
we made a boo-boo we put all the copies
in one place so nobody else probably
that's the karma right
so nobody else could get them and then
they all burned up
and then we ran away
and that's why i'm teaching you right
now and i'm like
so we started looking for tony llamas
any copies of tony loma's books
and finally jason dunbar who was a great
all
early
worker for all
he went to tibet and and he went to
chhoney monastery
and he begged for uh scans of choni
lama's
books and he got them okay
and he got all of them and i'd like to
show you one here
okay and you
know in those days uh coffee machines in
in east tibet
tony district
uh they weren't too good but you can see
it's a pretty cool carving
and uh
that's that's what it looks like okay
the end paper the the the
sideways letters on the left side
they say
which means
means commentary and somewhat of his
real text on wisdom
so
you find the name of the book
is at the end and then the page number
is there which is
which means 67 okay
and then there'll be a volume number
which is probably not
and uh
that means his collected works are
multiple volumes so if the page gets
separated from the book which often
happens
because they're not bound together then
you can find the book and put it back in
because teachers are always giving pages
to their students and saying memorize
that give me back the page tomorrow and
they never do
and so
uh so there's the copy from uh choney
monastery
and it was the only copy that we could
find and so
anytime we had a question we didn't have
any place to check
uh we didn't have anything to compare it
to you see there was no other carving
available to us
and it often happens that you have a
question about
a carbon is the carbon correct or not so
then we ended up going to russia
uh we found
i don't know 141 000
tibetan manuscripts
in the collection of the king the tsar
of russia had a collection
that he
he was a book collector russians are in
veteran book collectors they love books
and he collected 121 000 manuscripts and
we found a second copy
okay so here's a you can see in the next
picture
uh this is a copy of tony loma's works
much better carving as you can see
and more clear okay and uh
it took uh
12 years
to catalog those books it took 12 years
not to copy them not to scan them it
took 12 years to write the names done
okay
and we had three guys working full-time
and this and then once we saw
in the contract we had something in the
contract that said
we can we can make copies of our
monasteries books
and we got permission to make copies let
me see that copy again
uh now
if the guy holding the paper down while
the roller is going across the ink on
the wood block looks up
at some
probably not a girl but something
and
then you get these big stripes down the
down the page you see on the right side
this blank spot
and then you know gishla has to try to
guess what was there
on the wood block and it's really really
difficult sometimes so it's very
important
to have multiple wood blocks you know
it's very very important to go around
the world
and try to find
another copy okay and it takes money
to fly from east to bed to russia
it takes money to talk russians into
letting you work on their books for 12
years
and that's what you guys are fundraising
for okay it takes a lot of money it has
i would say five to ten million dollars
so far
and we're about five percent finished
so you know if you
if we want to have these classes and if
we want to be released from the chains
that bind us to samsara whoever it is
that is bounties inside
we need these books and then we need
money you know it costs money to fly
around
and go into ancient libraries and spend
months and months years 12 years
it takes money those guys who lived in
saint petersburg st petersburg is
is the most expensive european city
because you can't grow anything there
you know when i went there
they said don't spend much money on
dinner so i said
okay
and so i went to dinner i said all i
want is a salad
you know and they gave me a salad the
next day i said okay i didn't spend much
money on dinner
what'd you buy i bought a salad oh my
god that's the most expensive thing you
know
that's like 50
i'm like whoa why they said you're in
russia it's too cold you can't grow
vegetables here duh you should have had
some sheep meat or something
so it costs money to stay there it costs
money to a lot of money to stay there
for 12 years and also
all kinds of problems we got one of our
stuff got kidnapped by the mafia
in russia they said 50 000 bucks so
we're gonna kill him
and you know that's expensive
uh so anyway
one more thing i want to show you of why
john brady is so brilliant and why his
project deserves your help so much let's
see the next slide
okay
now this is the wood block
from choni monastery okay probably it
was printed sometime around 1700 i mean
carb
around 1700 and
if you know tibetan
uh
look at the fourth line okay tim
you want to read it slowly from shin
gestalt is preparing for this class and
gesh law is going crazy because it
doesn't make sense
okay there's something wrong here okay
like gesha
after many many years you smell
something's missing
like just something's missing here okay
and by the way tim you can appreciate it
he's got pairs here he's got members of
pairs
he's got gu and dibble
cause and effect later he's gonna have
sort of a and sort of
the feeling and the
feeler and then between that
you've got
thing defined with no definition
you've got thing defined
it's a list of pairs
but there's a one single guy in the
middle
okay it should have what word is missing
this is what is defined
we need the word for
definition
singing cheney is missing here okay so
geslav spends three hours
his struggle struggle struggle struggle
and then he says the goddamn block is
something wrong with the block that guy
was also looking up at something
and didn't carve definition
okay
in the block you know
so what does geshela do
yeah i gotta go find the other block but
if if all hasn't had the money to fly to
saint petersburg and stay there for 12
years i won't have a second block
got it that's why we need the gold club
and that's why you guys have to support
the gold club even five dollars even one
dollar
if there's enough
mice they can hold up the titanic
okay
that's the whole story with the gold
clubs is we're not
it's not big rich people it's a bunch of
small people who give one dollar five
dollars ten dollars and then we hold up
the titanic so i want to play with you
gesla decided there's something missing
from the block geschlag went to the
second block let's go see it
okay by the way i did this in the car
this morning
now
tim
read the third line
yeah what's there
the word that gets not predicted should
be there
okay there's definition
and senshi go back go back
make it big
now
hundred dollars
how the hell did they change the wood
block
somebody corrected it like 200 years ago
somebody
sat there like this left for three hours
and said something's wrong here
and then they corrected it
but what how do you correct the wood
block
you shave off the letters
and you dig a a square spot
then you take a piece of wood and make
it the same size and you glue it into
the block and then you recarve it but
there's no room to recarve it because
we're adding a word so what do you do
you shrink everything
look at the third line
it's very cool
you shrink everything he's trying to the
guy's trying to carve it like this you
know
this guy could he could you just fit in
two more words what
come on you can do it you know and you
can see this guy sitting in their car it
would take about
i don't know three four hours to carve
it
and he's carving everything smaller so
if you look at the picture
you can see that it's very cool to me
some guy took the block
cut out the
missing part
and glued it in and and that's why it's
smaller okay got it cool
isn't that cool
now if if gold club doesn't send guys to
saint petersburg library
then i cannot explain the book to you
because there's something wrong with the
book
got it and then it's wrong forever you
know if we don't fix it now no trust me
no one else cares about it
so yeah i think it's cool all right now
let's go to the impossible book
the book's already impossible
but if there's words missing it gets a
little more difficult
all right here we go
don't forget we're talking about
being chained chingua means chained
right
chained who's chained to what by the way
we are changed to what
mind your body which are uh oops messed
up
okay we're chained to a messed up body
of mind okay we are chained to a mortal
body
and we are chained to a
f'ed up mind
okay
that's the chance okay got it
who's chain
michael
okay michael is chained
to a messed up body in mind okay
is michael the chain
no i mean you chain somebody to a wall
in a dungeon right you chain a prisoner
to the wall
where's is the chain part of the wall or
is the chain part of the prisoner
neither i mean it's it's between the
prisoner and the wall right
got it
so
and by the way in the abi dharma
the chain is a separate entity
it's very interesting
they say
there's your body and mind
and then there's putty
and the chain is some kind of mystical
third thing
that keeps
that keeps punchy chained to his body
then nagarjuna's like come on
you know either
the chain is part of the body and mind
or the chain is part of the guy who's
chained to the body of mine okay but the
chain you know where else the chain
gonna be the guy dies what happens the
chain just sits around then the whole
universe is filled with chains
you know
who's just kidding
okay who's chain and then i'm going to
skip to this lash line
uh
very similar spelling and exactly the
same pronunciation because it has a
prefix
for fifty dollars i'll give you a clue
it came before
it came in the second chapter 25 dollars
working yay 25 bucks for gyoza
awesome
all right oh he's cheating okay that's
all right don't tell me
yeah walking what's it got to do with
chains
hundred dollars
yeah wait he's he's showing me
yeah here where's the
where are you
yeah where's the
okay there's a part of the path that you
walked there's a part of path you
haven't
walked the onion the part of the path
that you're walking on
is supposed to be somewhere between but
you can't define it and that's very
similar to the idea of the
of the chains okay the middle point
the part of the path that you're
stepping on now gong because gomez
always active
stepping it's not really walking it's
putting your foot down
okay where's the part of your path
where is the exact part of the path of
the present moment
where's the present moment okay that's
where the chain is
guys it's cool right
where's the chin that's like halfway
between you and your body and mine
the guardian's like get it
halfway between you and your body and
mind okay
uh so let's do the let's do the language
here
uh celtic nero and chinga if you are
if you are
chained to your
body and mind
near and lengthy ching mingyur
then you're not changing
if the chain is part of your body and
mind then the chain's not part of you
how's that
nero lend me
then
if you
let go of your body and mind you
wouldn't be chained anymore
if you died you wouldn't be changing
more you'd go to nirvana
if the chain is part of your messed up
body and mind then when you drop a body
in mind as you keep doing
then you should be unchained for a while
okay
neck up conscious
then what point is it where you're
chained okay
now
same argument you tell me where it comes
from okay for a hundred dollars
god you guys are making so much money
today
ready
everybody's like
did the chains exist before the guy was
chained
now what's the hundred dollars question
you take me back to a previous verse in
this series of classes
that's good but we were talking before
that
by the way the the the ninth chapter's
name
is was there something there before the
ninth chapter's name
is an is a uh investigation of whether
something was there before
and it referred to one of the senses
yeah when you look at something
yeah
is the eye there
it's the little girl with the telescope
there
she walks outside
and then the stars are there
okay
does the perceiver come first or the
scene comes first which one
does the little girl walk out with the
telescope and then looks at the stars or
how does it work
does the little girl with the telescope
walk out of her house and then look at
the stars
she has to she has to because there has
to be a telescope before there's a
astronomy
okay but she can't because
she's not a
astronomer until she looks at the stars
so it's the whole thing's impossible now
take that here
chains did the chains come first or the
chain came first
yeah good you can't be attaining until
you've been chained right but you gotta
have chance to get chained first
okay the whole thing is something
messed up okay
and the point is
if there's trouble in the kitchen
figuring out why the husband's upset you
have to look for other options
maybe it's all coming from you maybe
it's all coming from you
okay that's the that's the bottom line
maybe it's all coming from you
maybe you make the telescope and then
you make the girl and you make the
astronomy
all coming from you but they are not
causing each other out there
though it looks like the
but it's really
okay
that's all
if you realize it's duck duck duck then
you can do medicine to the mantra
but if you think you're duck duck duck
you're in trouble
if you're if you're out there doing
medicine for the mantras you're in
trouble
if you realize that the mantra comes
from you the illness comes from you the
fixing comes from you then you can use a
mantra
cool
yay let's go to the next one
oh by the way
next picture is the guy shackled or not
wait no the guy before that
is this guy shackle
no because there's no chains here
therefore the chains have to come first
right
never mind all right okay
next verse
uh
okay
this is very subtle it says
uh reshikh means uh
provisionally okay for the time being
okay for now rishik for now
mutual day
you cannot
take off your chains okay
let's let's
look
okay it's kind of like look look
you can't take off your chains why
first of all he's like that first of all
regardless first of all you cannot take
off your chip you cannot take off these
chains
you cannot not fight with your husband
you cannot take off these chains
why
because you see the chain
okay you
you cannot take off the chains why
because you think those chains are
coming this way
then you
the way you think about the chains is
the chain
got it okay you can he just says hey
let me tell you something what you can't
take these chains off
why because these chains are coming this
way
okay and thinking they're coming this
is the real chance
it's very sexy
thinking that chains are coming this way
when you look at the changes the real
chain and if you look at the chains then
you're gonna be chained more and more
you guys okay got it
very sexy
matching paion dreaming here even if i
took the chains off you would still be
cheating
okay
got it
if there was a middle point in the
stepping of the foot on the path
between being chained and unchained okay
uh then
in the same
then somewhere the part of the path
where you have been
and the part of the path where you will
be have to
touch if there's a place between chained
and unchained that can touch
then you can be chained and unchained in
the same moment it's not possible
like you can see nagarjuna going
okay we can make a dance right rebecca
some kind of hawaiian thing
okay
okay next verse
[Music]
let's just start with the first two
lines because this gets heavy this gets
difficult okay
if i could not near remember that would
be
dipper
if i could stop near a number in
i could reach nirvana
what's nearer limba
yeah if i could stop taking on new
bodies and minds
that's nirvana you know if i could stop
taking on
cancer-filled bodies
and anger-filled minds
well that would be nevada you know if i
could stop that
young day doctor giro shea
i would like to make
nirvana my own
dark cure
uh
okay i would like to make nirvana my own
then you're already in trouble because
me my me and my
that's the definition of the
misunderstanding which is which link of
the wheel of life
the blind man
which link
number one causes everything else okay
the minute you say i want nirvana
then you're already in trouble who's me
who's i what nirvana okay
means i want to make it mine
but
christina
the word for mine in
the word for me
also means
self nature
when we say dark main no an anatman
anatman
the word for me
in tibetan and sanskrit is the word
for self-existence
so when the guardian says hey
what do you want to do i want to reach
nirvana what do you want to do nirvana i
want to make it mine
oh yeah something said to mine yeah cool
got it
okay ackman i want the oddmen to own the
nirvana
but don't exist because ahmed means self
nature
all right data comes like
your desire to make nirvana your own is
just an advanced form of
misunderstanding
whoa
your desire to make nirvana you're my
own
is link number one in the goddamn wheel
of life
i want to get out of the real life yeah
okay how i'm going to make new run on my
own yeah cool that's the first link in
the real life
got it
you should be laughing i don't know
what's going on
let's do it again
i want to get out of the real life yeah
really what are you going to do i'm
going to make nirvana my own oh yeah
that's the first link in real life right
good very good
okay garlic it's kind of funny
all right uh
this is very difficult and you need
challenge okay
the the line says
any
uh
nowhere
could you create nirvana okay nowhere
could you get this is the d k with the d
which means to create as opposed to be
born
without the d
be born
with the d
create what's the most famous use of
this verb
that's pretty close
that's actually true how about simki
to give birth to their mind to give
birth to their wish for enlightenment
so
but here
okay 100 question god you guys are
making so much money today
which means to create
you know you want to create your nirvana
right you want to bring
you want to
create your nimana okay
he says the word create here is a code
word for drum dog in that pair called
drone dog and corndog
yay hundred dollars
jigme can you pay jimmy 100
now which cheapmate takes the money and
which gmat gives the money
and where's the line between
yeah overrate okay so what's it mean
here
when you say i want to make nirvana mine
you are
creating a
fake nirvana
you are creating a self-existent nevada
when you say i want to make nirvana mind
you are creating nevada and and then
chony lama says when the guardian says
create here
he means a self-existent number okay got
it
okay
you remember
you couldn't also remove that nirvana
somewhat here
which before meant a jedi for a hundred
dollars
damn
to drive okay before
someone meant to to drive right
uh the existence of a thing here it
means
like clear light somewhere
to remove okay
if you try to make a nirvana yours which
is self-existent that would be also an
abundant that would always be the same
and could never
what do you think nirvana is okay what
do you think nirvana is
okay that's who's asking
chishi
i'm sorry
what do you you guys
you guys who are creating a nirvana what
do you think so far
what do you think
what do you think so science now
you want to know some frustrating thing
the answer is missing from both carvings
the answer is missing from both carbons
okay it's amazing
nobody noticed it for
370 years
okay
i don't know what's going on i don't
know what they're doing in those
monasteries
uh
but
it's in the tenure it's in the garden
okay the guard the line exists
in the carving of
of nagarjuna
because he's quoting the birth parents
so i went and found it there thank god
for
club durham
so i can go find it in another
from india i found it from india okay
and the line was missing the whole line
was missing
the answer to the question what do you
think sansara was anyway
and then the cancer is wrong the answer
is missing so here's the answer
okay
[Music]
here's dark
yeah
okay
what the hell did you come up with
in your mind when you were wondering
what the hell was sansara
okay okay
what'd you come up with when i asked you
we're talking about nirvana right which
is freedom
but when i ask you what the heck is
sansa you start wandering around talk
a dumb
paricha
okay you went the wrong way in your
examination got it you did a a
a stupado prediction
stupido
okay you did a dumb you did a dumb
prediction okay got it you guys
that's the missing line now maybe it was
impolite and he didn't want to have it
uh
let's look at the picture here
if you can explain the picture to me
it's a roulette wheel
what's the point
in your pursuit of nirvana
in your pursuit of nirvana you are
well
you have a very slim chance to think
you're just going around
you're spinning the wheel again
the way you pursue nirvana spins the
samsara again
yeah cool good job
you're in pursuit of a nirvana for me
uh spin safari again congratulations you
know your pursuit of nirvana is spinning
samsara again
okay that's the point here
and i would i would say i don't want to
scare you but doing medicine of mantras
the wrong way
would make you sick
okay could sustain the suffering of your
body
okay i'm not saying you get cancer from
doing messenger mantras i'm not saying
that but what i am saying is
it's possible to do them
in us in a misunderstood way
which would sustain illness
okay it would spin samsara rather than
stopping the wheel okay
that's heavy that's heavy okay
we have to understand that
to make the mantras work we already have
to protect life or the mantra won't work
and you will die while you're doing
mantras
got it
okay
uh
it's a good time yeah depressed time
to go yes question
does that mean i should stop doing
mantis if i don't understand emptiness
now you should keep doing mantras why
because when you do mantras you haven't
generally
you have a
you have a foundational
sweet intent
and that foundational sweet intent
will help you understand
emptiness later so if
if you don't understand how the mantra
works keep doing the mantra because it
can help you understand how the mantra
works but
don't go too slow to understand how the
mantra works because you will die first
really seriously no no junk
but yeah anytime you do a mantra
it's a good scene maybe for future life
if you don't work on emptiness at the
same time so do your mantras for half an
hour go read nagarjuna for 10 minutes
come back to your mantras for half an
hour that's a good balance okay
but don't ignore nagajana and say i'm
gonna sit all day and do munches
because it's very possible you will die
before the before you get the benefit
from the mantras okay or you help
anybody
so keep sprinkling in
the sugar
of nagarjuna
and don't say it's too hard for me
because
sansar is hard and you gotta figure it
out
okay all right get to know sanskrit yay
let's talk about sansara sansara okay
hey you got that yeah
the pronunciation is sunstarter what's
that note at the bottom
please don't pronounce this as samsara
okay
that's a mistake
about the m
with a dot under it okay m
with a dot under it is not
m
okay they just didn't have any other
letter to use
i'm sorry okay so please
it's not m
it's emma with a dollar and with a
daughter
means like those french guys like
coquette
okay
cause they talk like
[Music]
don't say i'm sorry
it happened that adam the british made
this mistake
and and it got stuck every time i start
studying some sort of samsara sounds
like a guy's name right hey
meet my friend sam
sarah okay
and it's especially irritating to me by
the way
recently somebody put out a video
with my picture in it and the sanskrit
was all misspelled please don't do that
it makes me crazy okay so if you're
gonna use my name on my picture please
please please please let me check it
first okay
and and somebody else had tibetan it was
all misspelled
in the same time
so please please
you know because i feel maybe you can
see i feel passionate about it
okay uh so sri lanka is misspelled
steven on the yoga centers is misspelled
because they just they dropped the
diacritic they dropped the pronunciation
sign
in the same way that the dot got drawn
from the m
so here's this poor mr sivananda whose
name is mispronounced
forever
and this poor country whose name is
mispronounced forever it's sri lanka
it's not sorry
okay
but the dot got dropped off yeah okay
got it same thing with
samsara
okay
question if you want to irritate
gasoline
you know how
okay some means to be together along
with
by the way by itself it's some
and then sir means to flow
and the european is sir also and it's
found in serum
which is a flowing stuff
and strudel which is interesting
comes from sir
because of the uh
the whirlpool look of a good cinnamon
roll
okay
and doesn't that make sense for the
sanskrit of
are inextricably committed
if you ever have a strudel give it to me
and i can take care of it
because that's sunshine same root
all right
uh
that finishes
let's review what happened
we were trying to find
who is it that's gonna get to nirvana
and who is it that is chained to their
body and mind and you guys gotta think
about it you know
everyone says i want to get to nirvana
everybody says i want to escape the
wheel of life
did you notice the houses in the wheel
of life did you notice the two guys in
the boat in the wheel of like who's the
two guys in the boat right
ming su
name yeah body and mind it's by your
mind okay
when you get out of the wheel you're
gonna have to leave behind the
boat
with the body in mind in it well then
who's left
are you gonna go around without a body
of mine
here meet my friend i can't see him yeah
i'm sorry he don't got a body
what does he think about democrats and
replicas well he doesn't think he
doesn't have a mind he left that behind
in the wheel of life
where is
you he
to think about it you you keep saying
you want to go to nirvana what's that i
want to dump this body which is going to
get cancer sooner or later okay no
matter what you drink
now and i want to get rid of this mine
which is all messed up with jealousy etc
etc
okay
what happens after you get rid of it
oh i didn't think about it
i want to get off this bus
then you're standing out in the middle
doesn't
you say you want to get off the bus yeah
but i didn't
i wasn't thinking what would be left
over
you know all right you got to think
about it okay
see you in the next class
you